Doug MacGregor Papers
Doug MacGregor Papers
1952-2005
1976-2004
MacGregor, Doug
5.0 linear ft.
Original editorial cartoons and sports cartoons including MacGregor's student work at Syracuse University as well as publications and clippings.
2655692
Biographical History
Douglas MacGregor, professionally known as Doug MacGregor, is an American cartoonist. He received his BFA from Syracuse University in 1979.
Doug MacGregor grew up in Binghamton, New York and began his cartooning career drawing sports cartoons for the Daily Orange newspaper while a student at Syracuse University. He also served as the art director for the Report newspaper and his illustrations appeared on Syracuse Orange basketball programs. After receiving a BFA in Illustration in 1979, he landed a post as an editorial cartoonist for the Norwich (Conn.) Bulletin in 1980 where he drew five cartoons a week. Influenced by Cincinnati Enquirer cartoonist, Jim Borgman, MacGregor also credits one of his social studies teachers with getting him interested in current events.
His work received national exposure early-on, appearing occasionally on the opinion page of USA Today and one of his cartoons depicting Ronald Reagan was selected for the cover of the 1982 edition of the Best Editorial Cartoons of the Year. MacGregor's tenure with the Fort Myers (Fla.) News-Press began in 1988. In 1997 he began drawing a local comic strip titled Sunny Side Up which explores life in southwest Florida. MacGregor's cartoons appear through syndication in several other Florida newspapers.
MacGregor is a member of both the American Association of Editorial Cartoonists and the National Cartoonists Society. He has received numerous state and national awards, including multiple Best of Gannett awards. Several published collections of MacGregor's cartoons have appeared including, A Collection of MacGregor Editorial cartoons from the Norwich bulletin (1988) and Doug MacGregor's Cartoons: A Twenty-five Year Retrospective, released in 2005.
Doug MacGregor also draws freelance cartoons, illustrates children's books and self-syndicates his work.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Doug MacGregor Papers are divided into 4 series. The first series, Editorial cartoons offers examples of MacGregor's work as an editorial cartoonist from 1980 to 2004. The cartoons were published in the Norwich (Conn.) Bulletin and the Fort Myers (Fla.) News-Press. Major subjects include U.S. presidents (particularly Bill Clinton), elections, sports, the O.J. Simpson trial, education and foreign relations.
The majority of the cartoons are originals, although several laser prints are included. Most of the cartoons are labeled on the back with stickers listing a letter and a number, reflecting MacGregor's organizational scheme. Items labeled with the "I" prefix include 5 unfinished drawings, including 4 done in color. Several cartoons have stickers on the back with more details about the particular event depicted. Sizes vary, but most are approximately 11 ½" x 14 ½" and many are matted. The majority of the cartoons were drawn with pen and ink and there are several cartoons done in color. See the detailed inventory for more information on the medium.
The second series, Syracuse University cartoons and illustrations contains examples of MacGregor's student work at Syracuse University (1976-1979). Included are 16 original sports cartoons (with one self portrait) drawn for the student newspaper, the Daily Orange and three pieces of color, original artwork used on the cover of Syracuse Orange basketball programs (copies of the programs are included). It is worth nothing that MacGregor's sports cartoons appeared during a time of controversy over the university's Saltine Warrior mascot. Many of MacGregor's cartoons depict the traditional American Indian mascot as well as a newer version of the mascot appearing as a Roman warrior.
Publications contains five complete issues of the Daily Orange (1952, 1977) with cartoons by MacGregor, four issues of the Report newspaper (1978) for which MacGregor was art director and issues of other Syracuse University publications including Syracuse Poems (one issue contains artwork by MacGregor), Syracuse Review and Orange Crush. There are also several published collections of MacGregor's work.
Clippings contains several clippings of MacGregor's sports cartoons from the Daily Orange and an article from the Syracuse Herald Journal about changes to the Syracuse University mascot.
Arrangement of the Collection
Editorial and sports cartoons have been arranged in the order in which they were received using MacGregor's alphanumeric system. Full newspapers and clippings have been arranged in chronological order. Publications are alphabetical by title.
Related Material
has collections of over one hundred cartoonists. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Separated Material
A signed, published compilation of MacGregor's cartoons, Doug MacGregor's Cartoons: A Twenty-five Year Retrospective (2005) has been removed from the collection and sent to Rare Books.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Cartoonists; MacGregor, Doug.; Bush, George, 1924- -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Bush, George W. (George Walker), 1946- -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Carter, Jimmy, 1924- -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Clinton, Bill, 1946- -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Hussein, Saddam, 1937-2006 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Perot, H. Ross, 1930- -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Reagan, Ronald -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Simpson, O. J., 1947- -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Daily orange.; News-press (Fort Myers, Fla.); Norwich bulletin (Norwich, Conn.); American wit and humor, Pictorial.; Caricatures and cartoons -- Connecticut.; Caricatures and cartoons -- Florida.; Caricatures and cartoons -- Syracuse (N.Y.); Caricatures and cartoons -- United States.; Cartoonists -- Connecticut.; Cartoonists -- Florida.; Cartoonists -- United States.; Editorial cartoons -- Connecticut.; Editorial cartoons -- Florida.; Editorial cartoons -- United States.; Indians as mascots.; Persian Gulf War, 1991 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Sports team mascots -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Sports -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Student newspapers and periodicals.; Syracuse Orange (Basketball team) -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Syracuse Orange (Football team) -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Syracuse University -- Alumni and alumnae.; Syracuse University -- Caricatures and cartoons.; World politics -- 1945-1989 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; World politics -- 1989- -- Caricatures and cartoons.; United States -- Politics and government, 1945-1989 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; United States -- Politics and government, 1989- -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Cartoons (humorous images); Black-and-white photographs.; Editorial cartoons.; Newspapers.; Magazines (periodicals); Periodicals.; Programs (documents); Cartoonists.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Doug MacGregor, 2005, 2014.
Three unnumbered SU cartoons, transfer from University Archives, 2006.
Box 1, transfer from Unviersity Archives, 2018.
Inventory
- Editorial cartoons
  - Editorial cartoons, 1980-1984; 1987-1996,; 1998-2004 (Oversize 1)
    P 1 Jesse's Fax Paus 1984 - original/pen and ink
    P 2 Run for the Rose Garden 1988 - original/pen and ink
    P 3 Jimmy junction 1981 - original/pen and ink on Grafix paper
    P 4 Carter's Killer Rabbit 1980 - original/pen and ink
    P 5 Agent Orange Remedy/Air Force 1983 - original/pen and ink on Grafix paper
    P 6 Acid Rain and Mary Poppins 1981 - original/pen and ink on Grafix paper
    P 7 The Ghost of Christmas Future/Agent Orange 1983 - original/pen and ink on Grafix paper
    P 9 Reagan Cruise Control 1984 - original/pen and ink on Grafix paper
    P10 Gary Hart Wins the Hearts of New England 1984 - grease pencil on coquille paper
    P11 Reagan Revolution at the '96 GOP Convention 1996 - original/pen and ink
    P12 Clinton/Whitewater Tornado Season 1996 - original/pen and ink
    P13 Perot and NAFTA 1993 - original/pen and ink
    P14 Bush - Dukakis Debates 1988 - original/pen and ink on Grafix paper
    P15 Larger Than Life Leaders 1989 - original/airbrush Floro 4-color on acetate
    P16 Putting Iraq Over A Barrel Oil Embargo 1990 - original/airbrush Floro 4-color on acetate
    P17 Bolstering Poll Numbers/George Bush 1991 - original/pen and ink on Grafix paper
    P18 Cuomo, Clinton and Gore/Democratic Convention 1992 - original/Guache and Ink
    P19 Lessons From Vietnam/Bosnian Serbs 1995 - original/pen and ink
    P20 Peace Peril in Bosnia-Herzegovina 1995 - original/pen and ink
    P21 Serb Forces in Bosnia-Herzegovina 1995 - original/pen and ink
    P22 Giant Sucking Sound/Ross Perot Debates 1993 - original/pen and ink
    P23 Joycelyn Elders Loose Cannon 1993 - original/pen and ink
    P24 Clinton and Castro Deal With Cuban Refugees 1995 - original/pen and ink
    P25 GOP's Dead Horse Cemetery/Waco/Whitewater 1995 - original/pen and ink
    P26 Perot's Campaign Financing 1992/1996 1996 - original/pen and ink
    P27 Clinton/Gore Teflon 1996 - original/pen and ink
    P28 Perot's Anti-Incumbency Cauldron 1994 - original/pen and ink
    P29 Clinton vs. GOP Budget Impasse 1996 - original/pen and ink
    P30 Clinton Impeachment/The Presidential Seal 1998 - original/pen and ink
    P31 The Dow's Irrational Exuberance 1999 - original/pen and ink
    P32 Presidential Field of Dreams 2001 - original/pen and ink
    P33 Bush Inaugural Podium 2000 - original/pen and ink
    P36 Hairy John Kerry 2004 - black and white laser print
    P37 Tinker Bush, 'You Can Fly" 2004 - color laser print
    P44 Mirror Mirror: George W. Bush 2003 - black and white laser print
    P45 Saddam the Grinch 2002 - black and white laser print
    PC1 Sing-A-Long Song Sheet/Rappers 2 Live Crew 1990 - original/pen and ink on Grafix Paper
    PC2 Yes, Virginia, Santa is on a Diet 1999 - original/pen and ink
    PC3 Peace in All Languages 2000 - original/pen and ink
    PC4 Airline Maintenance Records 1996 - original/pen and ink
    PC5 Brain Stem Wars 1999 - original/pen and ink
    PC6 A Sealed Future 1987 - original/pen and ink on Grafix Paper
    PC7 Run For Your Life! 1982 - original/pen and ink on Grafix Paper
    PC8 Cheers TV Show Ends 1993 - original/pen and ink
    PC9 A 90s American Bedtime Story 1993 - original/pen and ink
  - Editorial cartoons, 1985; 1987,; 1989-2004 (Oversize 2)
    C 1 Having Enough Time in the 1990s 1996 - original/pen and ink
    C 2 NRA/Maternity Ward 2000 - original/pen and ink
    C 3 In Greenspan We Trust 1996 - original/pen and ink
    C 4 Household Names in the News 1994 - original/pen and ink
    C 5 Violence on TV 1994 - original/pen and ink
    OJ 1 OJ Trial Divides the US 1997 - original/pen and ink
    OJ 2 Watching the OJ Trial in the US 1995 - original/pen and ink
    OJ 3 OJ Trial Becomes News Diversion 1995 - original/pen and ink
    OJ 4 OJ Moves to Florida/Bankruptcy Paradise 1997 - original/pen and ink
    OJ 5 OJ and the Civil Suit 1995 - original/pen and ink
    S 1 Tourists, Full Speed Ahead 2002 - original/pen and ink
    S 7 Airport Arrivals 1997 - original/pen and ink
    S 9 Drawing Straws 1995 - original/pen and ink
    S10 Death Row 1997 - original/pen and ink
    S12 Prize Trophy/George W. & Al Gore in Florida 2000 - original/pen and ink
    S13 Not Short On Republicans 2001 - original/pen and ink
    S14 Electric Cars 1998 - pen and ink on photocopy paper
    S15 Polluter-In-Chief/George W. Bush 2001 - original/pen and ink
    S16 The Y2K Compliant Circus Tent/Florida 1999 - original/pen and ink
    S17 Bush & Gore Looking For Florida Swing Voters 2000 - original/pen and ink
    S18 George and Jeb Bush Photo-Op/Everglades 2001 - original/pen and ink
    S26 Brush Firefighters 1998 - original/pen and ink
    S40 Florida Beaches of the Future? 1995 - original/pen and ink
    S41 The Other Connecticut/Per Capita Income 1987 - original/pen and ink on Grafix paper
    E 1 Today's Alphabet 1995 - original/pen and ink
    E 2 Student Desktops Then & Now 1997 - original/pen and ink
    E 3 Future Workforce 1998 - original/pen and ink
    E18 Future College Coaches 2000 - original/pen and ink
    SP 2 Self-Portrait 2002 - original/pen and ink w/o Photoshop
    SP 3 Steroids in Baseball 2004 - original/pen and ink w/o Photoshop
    SP 4 Steroids in Baseball 2004 - Photoshop/laser black and white print
    SP 5 Tyson Bites 1997 - original/pen and ink
    SP 6 Miami and Virginia Tech Leave Big East 2003 - original/pen and ink
    SP 7 Miami and Virginia Tech and BC Leave Big East 2003 - original/pen and ink
    T 1 What to do with Olympic Terrorists... 1996 - original/pen and ink
    T 2 United Nations Weaken 1995 - original/pen and ink
    T 3 The Nuts and Bolts of Iran/The Ayatollah Khoemini 1985 - grease pencil on coquille paper
    T 6 USS Stack Attacked 1987 - original/pen and ink on Grafix paper
    T 8 Fall of the Berlin Wall 1989 - original/airbrush Floro 4-color on acetate
    T 9 US Finding World Enemies 1990 - original/airbrush Floro 4-color on acetate
    T10 Spitting Out Hamas 1996 - original/pen and ink
    T11 Bush vs. Low Tech Terrorism 2001 - original/pen and ink
    T13 Comparing Scars/Vietnam War and Afghanistan 1988 - original/pen and ink on Grafix paper
    H 5 Big Bad Hurricane Season 1993 - original/pen and ink on Grafix paper
    I 1 Clinton Roller-Coaster 1996 - original/gouache and ink
    I 2 Clinton/Tsongas/Buchanan/Bush Tour Florida 1992 - original/gouache and ink
    I 3 Saddam Plays Chess/US Oil Embargo 1990 - original/gouache and ink
    I 4 Clinton Governorship vs. Presidency 1992 - original/gouache and ink
    I 5 Ross Perotism Popularity 1992 - grease pencil on coquille paper
  - Editorial cartoons, 1980-2005 (Oversize 5)
    Many of these are tributes to various individuals including Princess Diana, Rosa Parks, Charles Schulz, Alan Shepard Jr. and the 9/11 first responders. These appeared in either the Norwich-Bulletin (NB) or News-Press (NP). All are original pen and ink drawings. Numbering and descriptions wre provided by the donor.
    N-P 01 In Case of Emergency 1998 - President Clinton contemplates bombing Iraq to distract the country and the world from impeachment proceedings stemming from the Monica Lewinsky scandal
    NB 02 Bombs Away 1982 - Prime Minister Menachem Begin orders the bombing of the Osirak nuclear power plant in Iraq and the invasion of Lebanon to fight the PLO, igniting the Lebanon War
    NB 03 Ending Apartheid 1985 - The Anti-Apartheid protest movement continues in South Africa. More and more companies from around the world divest from the South African economy. Negotiations to end apartheid begin in 1990.
    NP 04 One Last Point of Light 1992 - Before George H.W. Bush exits the oval office he leaves one last point of light for president-elect Bill Clinton: the spoils and explosive remnants of the Gulf War.
    NP 05 Best Upstaging Role 1993 - First Lady Hillary Rodham Clinton surpassing her husband and President Bill Clinton in popularity as she crusades for the rights of woman and children around the world.
    NB 06 Big Ron's Body Shop & Brain-Washing Service 1981 - Beginning with the election of 1980, the popularity of President Ronald Reagan causes a sizable defection for Democrats. The Democrats that defected to support Reagan's policies were known as "Reagan Democrats"
    NP 07 Lobbyassic Park 1993 - Playing off the popularity of the recently released movie, Jurassic Park, this cartoon satirizes the immense power and influence of the lobbyists ruling Capitol Hill.
    NP 08 Peacekeeping in Mogadishu 1993 - Acting as part of the UN's peacekeeping forces, American servicemen are sent to Somalia to restore order so that international aid can be distributed. In that mission eighteen American servicemen are brutally killed from October 3-4, 1993.
    NP 09 Saddam's Nose of Destruction 1991 - A U.N. ultimatum is given to Iraqi leader Saddam Hussein on November 29, 1990. It stipulates that if the Iraqi dictator does not remove his troops from Kuwait by January 15, 1991, a US-led coalition will be authorized to drive them out.
    NB 10 Reagan Battle Head 1983 - As Commander in Chief from 1981 to 1989, Ronald Reagan fought to get the nation a 600-ship Navy. Spearheaded by aircraft carrier battle groups that could project power around the globe, Reagan's defense build-up took control of the world's oceans.
    NP 11 Clinton's Political Footballs 1993 - Early in President Clinton's tenure as president he is faced with many crucial and controversial issues including NAFTA legislation, healthcare reform, government waste and lobbying reform, among others.
    NB 12 Midwest Drought 1988 - One of the worst droughts in American history hits Midwestern states causing over $60 billion in damage.
    NB 13 Reagan Reform 1985 - President Ronald Reagan introduces the Tax Reform Act of 1986 that attempts to simplify the tax codes of the IRS.
    NP 14 White House Water Damage 1996 - Bill and Hillary Clinton avoid political damage from the Tumultuous Whitewater scandal while in office, unlike Richard Nixon whose Watergate Scandal rushed through his administration eventually forcing him to resign as Commander in Chief.
    NB 15 One Home, Fifty-Two To Go 1980 - Iranians hold fifty-two American diplomats captive for 444 days. One of the captives, Richard Queen, is released in July of 1980 after becoming ill. The remaining hostages are eventually released in January of the following year. It is a diplomatic crisis for President Jimmy Carter. It costs him the presidential election the same year, losing to GOP contender Ronald Reagan.
    NB 16 Reagan's Space Wars 1983 - The new "Star Wars" defense system approved by president Ronald Reagan is designed to destroy missiles from space. The Soviets feared the system would increase the risk of the United States launching a first attack because U.S. officials would not fear retaliation.
    NP 17 The 2000 Presidential Election and the U.S. Split Court 2000 - After a month of recounting votes in Florida between Republican George W. Bush and Democrat Al Gore, the U.S. Supreme Court makes a final 5-4 ruling in favor of Bush. Only 537 votes separated the two in the Sunshine State giving Bush the necessary electoral vote count to win.
    NP 18 Ding Dong, The Wicked Recession is Dead 1992 - The US Recession of 1989-1991 is finally over. Putting Americans back to work and ending the psychological effects of unemployment and economic gloom becomes the campaign issues of the 1992 election.
    NP 19 Read My Lips...Smell My Breath! 1990 - President George H.W. Bush refuses to raise taxes to reduce the national budget deficit. A recession in the U.S. continues until midway through 1991.
    NB 20 Dan Quayle Hunting 1988 - President George H.W. Bush chooses junior Indiana Senator Dan Quayle as his running mate in the 1988 election. Quayle was young and athletic and Bush had specifically chosen him to appeal to a younger generation of conservative Americans.
    NB 21 Paul "Bear" Bryant 1982 - Bear Bryant retires from college football with a record 323 wins in December of 1982. He died one month after coaching his last game.
    NB 22 Anwar Sadat 1981 - Egyptian President Anwar Sadat is assassinated on October 6, 1981 after negotiating with Israel's Prime Minister Menachem Begin for peace in the Middle East.
    NB 23 Henry Fonda 1982 - Hollywood and Broadway legend Henry Fonda passes away on August 12, 1982.
    NB 24 John Lennon 1980 - Music legend and Beatle John Lennon is tragically gunned down near his New York City apartment on December 8, 1980
    NP 25 Richard Nixon 1994 - 37th President of the United States Richard M. Nixon dies on April 22,1994.
    NP 26 Charles Kuralt 1997 - CBS journalist Charles Kuralt dies on July 4, 1997.
    NP 27 Alan Shepard, Jr. 1998 - Original Mercury and Apollo astronaut Alan Shepard dies on July 21, 1998
    NP 28 Victims of the Oklahoma City Bombing 2001 - Tribute to the fallen at the domestic terrorist bombing of the Oklahoma City Federal Building, April 19, 1995. This cartoon was drawn after convicted terrorist bomber was executed on June 11, 2001 for killing 168 people.
    NP 29 Carroll O'Conner 2001 - Tribute to actor Carroll O'Connor who immortalized the TV 1970's character Archie Bunker and his famous living room chair.
    NP 30 Awakening a Sleeping Giant 2001 - This cartoon appeared on September 12, 2001 in the News-Press, Fort Myers, FL. The day after the tragic 9/11 attacks on America.
    NP 31 Americans in Uniform Standing Tall Until the Very End 2001 -Tribute to 340 fallen firemen and 60 police officers that were killed trying to save victims of the 9/11 attacks. This cartoon appeared on September 13, 2001 in the News-Press, Fort Myers, FL.
    NP 32 Princess Diana 1997 -Tribute to Princess Diana who was tragically killed in a car crash on August 31 ,1997 after being chased by international paparazzi photographers.
    NP 33 Marjory Stoneman Douglas 1998 - Tribute to environmentalist, writer, journalist and feminist Marjory Stoneman Douglas who died on May 14,1998.
    NB 34 Martin Luther King, Jr. 1988 - Tribute to civil rights movement activist and humanitarian Martin Luther King, Jr. on the twentieth anniversary of his death.
    NP 35 Fred Lasswell 2001 - Tribute to cartoonist, Fred Lasswell who drew the popular comic strip, Barney Google and Snuffy Smith and died on March 4, 2001.
    NP 36 Charles "Sparky" Schulz 2000 - Tribute to legendary cartoonist, Charles Schulz who created and drew the popular comic strip, Peanuts, died on February 12,2000.
    NP 37 Chuck Jones 2002 - Tribute to legendary cartoonist and animator, Chuck Jones who created and animated several popular Looney Tunes, Merrie Melodies and Warner Brothers studio cartoon characters, died on February 22, 2002.
    NP 38 Herbert Block 2001 - Tribute to legendary editorial cartoonist Herbert "Herblock" Block who drew for nine decades, covering the issues and administrations of thirteen presidents. Block died on October 7, 2001.
    NP 39 Irving Berlin 1989 - Tribute to prolific American composer and lyricist Irving Berlin who died of natural causes on September 22, 1989 after living to be 101 years old.
    NP 40 Jay Leno 1992 - Comedian, actor and TV host Jay Leno steps into the permanent role of being Tonight Show host in 1992 after replacing legendary entertainer and host Johnny Carson.
    NP 41 Rosa Parks 2005 - "First Lady of the Civil Rights Movement", Rosa Parks passes away on October 24,2005. Her refusal to give up her seat on a Montgomery, Alabama bus on December 1, 1955 led to more civil rights civil disobedience in the movement to stop segregation in the South.
    NP 42 Lucille Ball 1989 - Tribute to female comedian and TV actress and star Lucille Ball who died on April 26, 1989.
    NP 43 Red Skelton 1997 - Tribute to comedian and TV actor Red Skelton who died on September 17, 1997.
    NP 44 Jeff MacNelly 2000 - Tribute to editorial cartoonist, comic strip artist and Pulitzer-prize winner Jeff MacNelly who died on June 8, 2000.
    NP 45 Al Hirschfeld 2003 - Tribute to caricaturist Al Hirschfeld who died on January 20, 2003.
- Syracuse University cartoons and illustrations
  - Basketball programs and original artwork, 6 Jan 1979; 8 Jan 1979,; 10 Jan 1979 (Oversize 5)
    3 pieces of original art used to illustrate the cover of S.U. Hoops, official program of Syracuse University varsity basketball, and 3 complete programs showing MacGregor's art
  - Cartoons, 1976-1979; undated (Oversize 3)
    SU 4 Self-Portrait/Mascot Cartoon/Photo 1979 - original/pen and ink/photo